Guide to the John Bruce Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Bruce collection
1835-1845
OSB MSS 73
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
Series I, Letters to John Bruce, consists almost entirely of business and professional letters addressed to him in his roles as Secretary of the Camden Society and editor of many of its early publications. Correspondents include Octavian Blewitt; Sir Robert Harry Inglis; William Jerdan; Macvey Napier; Julia Pardoe; and Thomas Joseph Pettigrew. Series II, Letters of Caroline Amelia Halsted, contains 35 letters from the popular historian to Bruce on the subjects of her royal biographies; her negotiations with publishers and research libraries; and her thoughts on her position as a woman historian.
Bruce, John, 1802-1869
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOHN BRUCE, 1802-1869
John Bruce was born in London and educated in England and Aberdeen. While he was trained in English law, he did not practice after 1840, and instead pursued his historical and antiquarian interests.
In particular, Bruce devoted much of his energy and attention to the newly important scholarly societies and publication projects of his day. Bruce held two offices in the Society of Antiquaries and wrote many articles for its journal, Archaelogia, including his "Inedited Documents Relating to the Condemnation and Imprisonment of Sir Thomas More" (xxvii, 10) and the "Inquiry into the Authenticity of the Paston Letters" (v. xli, 15). For the Parker Society he edited The Works of Roger Hutchinson (1842), and was co-editor of The Correspondence of Matthew Parker (1853) with T. T. Perowne.
Bruce was a principal founder and officer of the Camden Society, and contributed many of its early publications, including its first, The Historie of the Arrivall of Edward IV.... (1839). For the Society, Bruce edited selections of correspondence and documents relating to Elizabeth I, Robert Dudley, Earl of Leceister, Robert Cecil, Lord Burleigh, James I, and Charles I. In addition, Bruce edited the first publications of Letters and Papers of the Verney Family... (1853); the Liber Famelicus of Sir James Whitlocke (1858); and the Journal of a Voyage into the Mediterranean of Sir Kenelm Digby (1868). Bruce also offered advice and assistance to many historians and biographers of the period, including Caroline Amelia Halsted, the first biographer of Richard III to draw upon unpublished sources such as MS Harleian 433.
The project that occupied the final decades of his scholarly career was the 12 volumes of the Calendar of State Papers, Domestic Series, of the Reign of Charles I.... (1858-71). In 1861 he was appointed a Trustee of the Sir John Sloan's Museum. John Bruce died suddenly in London on October 28, 1869, his wife having predeceased him.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to John Bruce, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to May 2002 have been organized into two series.
Series I, Letters to John Bruce, has been arranged alphabetically by correspondent and contains business and professional letters addressed to Bruce, frequently in his role as an officer of the Camden Society. Topics include meetings, membership nominations, dues collection, and publication plans of the societies. Many of the letters date from the first years of the Camden Society's existence and offer support for the new venture. Lord Mahon, on the other hand, pointed out that "the Roxburgh, Bannatyne, Abbotsford and other societies already existing seem to be quite adequate to the purpose required," and declined to join the Camden (Box 1, folder 74).
Several correspondents address Bruce's personal scholarly pursuits. Letters by John Hymers and Cornelius Nickerson discuss the editing of Roger Hutchinson's works. The letters of Macvey Napier reveal his editorial policy for historical articles in the Edinburgh Review and explain his lack of interest in a Bruce submission: "nor have I ever heard of Sarah Martin, either by herself, or in connection with 'prison discipline.'...Look about you for an article similar to the last." Julia Pardoe's letters thank Bruce for his encouragement and request further advice. A. F. Holt of Eton College explains his failure to locate a volume in the college library: "the catalogue...is imperfect as it is, and the present position of the books does not, in any degree, correspond with it."
Finally, other letters offer more general insights into mid-nineteenth century scholarship. Letters from the widow and son of James Bird, including two to the popular royal biographer Agnes Strickland, concern the relief provided by the Literary Fund Society and George Bird's hope for Strickland's assistance in continuing to edit "Pawsey's Ladies' Pocket Book." The Rev. Robert Dixon's letters detail his attempts to rebuild the only college (and the only library) on the Isle of Man. Robert Eden, John Mee Mathews, and J. A. Cramer discuss their own research projects.
Series II, Letters of Caroline Amelia Halsted, contains chronologically arranged letters to Bruce, primarily on the writing of her Richard III as Duke of Gloucester and King of England (1844). Halsted requests extracts from the then-unpublished Croyland Chronicles; discusses her use of manuscript sources and society publications; sends Bruce completed chapters for "the pruning knife;" and asks advice on the selection of frontispieces, negotiatiing with her publisher, Longmans, and the appropriate use of gift copies.
Halsted's letters also reveal her strong sense of her position as a woman historian. As early as December 8, 1842, she expressed misgivings about writing "a book that...is almost too strong for a woman's pen." In a letter of February 28, 1844, she states: "I sometimes think I have too many notes--and too much Appendix--and yet I thought I ought to give my authorities, considering the suspicious way in which a woman's opinion wd. be viewed, unless well backed, on a subject so important ." Halsted also reminds Bruce that research for an essay on "'the progress of opinions' concerning Richard... could not be accomplished, except at the British Museum."
Her later letters contain requests for copies of reviews, comments on sales of Richard III, and discussions of her search for a new subject. While Halsted accepted Bruce's discouragement about Alfred the Great, and considered writing a biography of a woman, she rejected the idea that she should write fiction. "I have no imagination for fairy tales and I am too matter of fact for novels --but I love historical research; heart and soul goes to work on it." (Box 1, folder 81)
The Halsted letters also contain news of her travels and her home life, as well as repeated inquiries about the health of Mrs. Bruce and plans for visits to London.
Learned institutions and societies -- Great Britain; Learning and scholarship -- Great Britain; Scholars -- Great Britain; Women biographers; Women historians -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Intellectual life -- 19th century; Authors; Women authors; Blewitt, Octavian, 1810-1884; Bruce, John, 1802-1869; Halsted, Caroline A. (Caroline Amelia), 1803 or 1804-1848; Inglis, Robert Harry, Sir, 1786-1855; Jerdan, William, 1782-1869; Napier, Macvey, 1776-1847; Pardoe, Miss (Julia), 1804?-1862; Pettigrew, Thomas Joseph, 1791-1865; Camden Society (Great Britain); Society of Antiquaries of London
- Letters to John Bruce, 1835-1845; Series I; 0.30' (0.75 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Letters to John Bruce, is alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent.
  - ADAMSON, JOHN
    - ALS to JB; Newcastle upon Tyne, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ALLNATT, R. H.
    - 3 ALS to JB and ALS to "My dear Richards", 1840-41 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Concerning literary matters and the Society of Antiquaries
  - BARNWELL, CHARLES FREDERICK
    - ALS to "Sir Henry;" British Museum, 1840 Jan 21 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Proposing Rev. William Staunton for membership in the Camden Society.
  - BENNETT, J. W.
    - 3 ALS to JB; 3 Rosomon's Buildings, Islington, 1841-42 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BERGNE, JOHN BRODRIBB
    - 3 ALS to JB, 1842-45 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Concerning the Society of Antiquaries and the Numismatic Chronicle.
  - BIRCH, CHARLES
    - 2 ALS to JB, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Concerning the Camden Society; thanks for books. With: ALS to "My dear Knighte," n.d.
  - BIRD, EMMA (MRS. JAMES BIRD)
    - ALS to JB, 1839 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Thanking him for his assistance in the Literary Fund Society grant
    - ALS to Agnes Strickland, 1839 Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Thanking her for her assistance in the Literary Fund Society grant; describing needs of herself and her children
  - BIRD, GEORGE
    - ALS to Agnes Strickland, 1839 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Assuming editorship of "Pawsey's Ladies' Pocket Book;" news of his mother and siblings
  - BIRKBECK, THOMAS
    - ALS to JB, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Concerning his subscription
  - [BLACK, WILLIAM?]
    - ALS to JB; 16 Clements' Inn, 1837 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - BLEWITT, OCTAVIAN, 1810-1884
    - 17 ALS to JB, 1840-44 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Concerning business of the Camden Society and the Parker Society
  - BOSWORTH, JOSEPH, 1789-1876
    - ALS to JB; Carrington near Nottingham, 1841 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Concerning the Camden Society
  - BRÖMET, WILLIAM
    - 3 ALS to JB, 1841-42, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Concerning his membership in the Shakespeare Society; history of the wainscoting in Eton College Chapel
  - BRUCE, C. D.
    - 3 ALS to JB, 1835 Jun-Jul (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Concerning copies of the Domesday Book, including that belonging to "my uncle Lord Elgin"
  - BRYAN, G., REV.
    - 2 ALS to JB, 1840, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Concerning his research in the Wyatt Papers and the Camden Society
  - [CANDLER, JOSIAH?]
    - ALS to JB; Patent Office, 1837 Feb (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - CARLISLE, NICHOLAS, 1771-1847
    - ALS to JB; Somerset Place, 1843 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      With 3 printed forms completed by Carlisle, probably notifications of meetings of the Society of Antiquaries sent to JB, 1836-39
  - CARTHEW, GEORGE ALFRED, 1807-1882
    - 3 ALS to JB, 1839, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - CASSAN, STEPHEN HYDE, 1789-1841
    - ALS to JB, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Soliciting a subscription
  - CHRISTMAS, HENRY, 1811-1868
    - ALS to JB; Sion College, 1842 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - COCHRANE, JOHN GEORGE, 1781-1852
    - 5 ALS to JB; London Library, 1843 Feb-Nov (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Concerning research and Sir Harry Verney
  - COURTENAY, THOMAS PEREGRINE, 1782-1841
    - AL (in the third person) to JB, 1840 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - COXE, H. O. (HENRY OCTAVIUS), 1811-1881
    - ALS to JB, 1841 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Sending information on Roger of Wendover (not present)
  - CRAMER, J. A. (JOHN ANTHONY), 1793-1848
    - 2 ALS to JB; Oxford, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Concerning his progress on The Second Book of Nicander Nucius
  - DAVIES, THOMAS STEPHENS, 1795-1851
    - ALS to JB; Woolwich, 1839 Aug 28 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - DE GREY, THOMAS PHILIP DE GREY, EARL, 1781-1859
    - AL (in the third person) to JB; Newby Hall, [1839?] Aug 21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Concerning Camden Society
  - DEVON, FREDERICK
    - ALS to JB, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Complaining of a reviewer
  - DIXON, ROBERT, REV.
    - 4 ALS to JB; The College, Isle of Man, 1844-45 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Concerning his efforts to rebuild King William's College after the fire of January, 1844
  - [DURHAM, SAMUEL ASTLEY, D. 1858?]
    - ALS to JB; 29 Prebend St., Camden Town, 1843 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - DYCE, WILLIAM, 1806-1864
    - ALS to JB; School of Design, Somerset House, 1841 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - EDEN, ROBERT, 1803-1898
    - 4 ALS to JB, 1841-42, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Concerning his progress on Examinations and Writings of John Philpot for the Parker Society
  - EDWARDS, EDWARD, 1812-1886
    - 2 ALS to JB, 1840 May, Nov (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - FARR, EDWARD
    - ALS to JB, 1842 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Concerning "The Book of Revelation Demonstrated"
  - FENNELL, JAMES HAMILTON
    - ALS to JB; Hillingdon Heath, Uxbridge, Middlesex, 1843 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Soliciting a subscription to his work on Shakespeare's "Philosophical Knowledge"
  - GLOVER, [STEPHEN, D. 1869]?
    - ALS to JB; Reigate, 1840 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - GODWIN, GEORGE, 1815-1888
    - ALS to JB; Pelham Crescent, Brompton, 1843 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Requesting JB to mention his name "to any of the gentlemen named on the enclosed list" (not present)
  - GOODING, JONATHAN
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Stanhope, Philip Henry Stanhope, Earl, Box 1, folder 74
  - GROOME, ROBERT HINDES, 1810-1889
    - ALS to JB; Corfe Castle, Dorsetshire, 1839 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - [GWENNAP, T.]
    - ALS to JB; Tichborne Street, 1837 Oct (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Thanking him for the loan of Cramp's Text-Book of Popery, in which he found "more real arguments against Catholicism than all those Red-Hot Pugin may be able to unsay."
  - HARDING, GEORGE PERFECT, D. 1853
    - 2 ALS to JB; Hercules Buildings, Lambeth, 1839 May, Jun (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Soliciting support for his projected illustrated work
    - HARDY, JOHN STOCKDALE, 1793-1849
      - AL (in the third person) to JB; Leicester, 1836 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - HAWKINS, EDWARD, 1780-1867
    - ALS to JB; British Museum, 1843 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Concerning arrears of dues for the Camden Society
  - HODGSON, WILLIAM, REV.
    - 2 ALS to JB; St. Peter's College, Cambridge, 1841 Nov (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Arranging to loan JB the manuscript of "Campus Florum" from Peterhouse for the Camden Society's use
  - HOLT, A. F.
    - ALS to JB; Eton College, 1841 Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Concerning his failure to locate a requested book
  - HUSSEY, RICHARD CHARLES
    - ALS to W. J. Thomas; "at Mrs. Suthe1rland's, Merrow, Guildford", 1841 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Concerning Camden Society dues
  - HYMERS, JOHN, 1803-1887
    - 2 ALS to JB, 1841 Jun, Sep (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Concerning the Parker Society's interest in publishing the works of Roger Hutchinson
  - INGLIS, ROBERT HARRY, SIR, 1786-1855
    - 4 ALS and 2 engraved invitations, signed, to JB, 1838-41, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Concerning Camden Society matters
  - JENNER, CHARLES H.
    - ALS to JB; 1 Chesterfield St., 1840 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Concerning Sir Herbert Jenner's information on John Hayward
  - JENNER, HERBERT, SIR
    - ALS to JB; Chesterfield St., 1840 Jan 16 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Concerning John Hayward
  - JERDAN, WILLIAM, 1782-1869
    - 3 ALS to JB and circular letter, signed, 1839, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
      Circular letter solicits support for a plan to encourage "the Authors of England"
  - JERMYN, JAMES, D. 1852
    - 2 ALS to JB; Reydon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
      Concerning Camden Society business
  - KING, THOMAS WILLIAM, 1801-1872
    - ALS to JB; College of Arms, 1842 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Concerning ceremonial for the coronation of Henry VII. Signed, "Thos. Wm. King, Rouge Dragon"
  - KÖNIG, CHARLES DIETRICH EBERHARD, 1774-1851
    - 2 ALS to JB; British Museum, 1840 Jan, Feb (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - LANDON, WHITTINGTON HENRY, 1804-1883
    - ALS to JB; 4 Lincoln's Inn Fields, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 54)
      Informing him of his election to the Literary Fund Society Committee
  - LECHMERE, CHARLES
    - AL (in the third person) to JB; State Paper Office, n.y. Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      Enclosing copies (not present)
  - LICHFIELD, S.
    - ALS to H. Merivale, 1839 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      Proposing William Whateley for the Camden Society
  - LISTER, T. H. (THOMAS HENRY), 1800-1842
    - ALS to JB; Kenthouse, Knightsbridge, 1843 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - LODGE, JOHN
    - 3 ALS to JB; Magdalene College, Cambridge, 1838-39 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      Concerning the loan of manuscripts from Peterhouse
  - MANSEL, JAMES T.
    - ALS to JB, 1841 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 59)
      Declining to join the Society
  - MARKLAND, J. H. (JAMES HEYWOOD), 1788-1864
    - 2 ALS to JB, 1842, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 60)
      Camden Society business
  - [MATHEW, JOHN MEE]
    - ALS to JB enclosing ALS with notes to the Camden Society Board; Temple, 1842 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      Contains notes on Harl. MS 2307 and proposals for an edition
  - MERIVALE, JOHN HERMAN, 1779-1844
    - ALS to JB; Court of Bankruptcy, Basinghall St., 1839 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Will meet his "co-auditors" tomorrow
  - NAPIER, MACVEY, 1776-1847
    - 6 ALS to JB; Edinburgh, 1839-44?, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 63)
      Concerning The Edinburgh Review
  - NICHOLSON, CORNELIUS, 1804-1889
    - 2 ALS to JB; Caesar Head, Kendal, 1842 Dec (Box 1, Folder 64)
      Concerning provincialisms in the language of Roger Hutchinson
  - NICHOLSON, W.
    - ALS to W. M. Thomas, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - OUSELEY, GORE, SIR, 1770-1844
    - ALS to JB; 41 Upper Brook Street, 1840 Apr 25 (Box 1, Folder 66)
      Camden Society dues
  - PARDOE, MISS (JULIA), 1806-1862
    - 3 ALS to JB, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 67)
      Concerning literary matters and messages from her father. Signed, "J.S.H. Pardoe."
  - PARSONS, DANIEL
    - ALS to JB; 7 Richmond Hill, Bath, 1840 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 68)
      Declining to join the Camden Society
  - PENROSE, THOMAS
    - ALS to [John Bruce]; W-- Vicarage, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 69)
      Resigning from the Society
  - PETTIGREW, THOMAS JOSEPH, 1791-1865
    - 6 ALS to John Bruce; Savile Row, 1840-42, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 70)
      Society of Antiquaries business and social engagements
  - PIDGEON, HENRY CLARK, 1807-1880
    - ALS to John Bruce, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 71)
      Concerning his work on Roman and Anglo-Saxon costume. With sketches in pencil on tracing paper of two figures in Roman dress
  - ROBY, JOHN, 1793-1850
    - ALS and AL (in the third person) to John Bruce; Rochdale, 1839, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - ROSSER, W. H. (WILLIAM HENRY)
    - ALS to JB; 7 Warwick Court, Grays Inn, 1839 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 73)
      Invitation to a performance of a Christmas masque written for the Society of Noviomagus
  - STANHOPE, PHILIP HENRY STANHOPE, EARL, 1805-1875
    - ALS to Lord Henniker; Walmer, 1838 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 74)
      Declining to join the Camden Society. Signed, "Mahon." Followed by ALS from Jonathan Gooding to Lord Henniker, 1838 Dec 7, regretting Mahon's refusal but reporting that the "Society goes on well."
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - ALS to JB; London, 1845 Feb 8 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - ALS to JB, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 76)
- Letters from Caroline Amelia Halsted, 1841-1845; Series II; 0.20' (0.25 box)
  Series II, Letters from Caroline Amelia Halsted, is chronologically arranged.
  - 6 ALS to JB, 1841-42 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - 7 ALS to JB, 1843 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - 7 ALS to JB, 1844 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - 7 ALS to JB, 1844 May-Dec (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - 8 ALS to JB, 1845 Jan-Oct (Box 1, Folder 81)